<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<component type="desktop-application">
  <id>com.boo.app</id>
  <metadata_license>CC0-1.0</metadata_license>
  <project_license>MIT</project_license>

  <name>Boo</name>
  <summary>Local speech-to-text overlay</summary>

  <developer id="io.github.ilovepixelart">
    <name>ilovepixelart</name>
  </developer>

  <url type="homepage">https://github.com/ilovepixelart/boo</url>
  <url type="bugtracker">https://github.com/ilovepixelart/boo/issues</url>
  <url type="vcs-browser">https://github.com/ilovepixelart/boo</url>

  <!-- Transcribes the user's own speech locally; no content of any kind is
       generated, exchanged, or transmitted. -->
  <content_rating type="oars-1.1"/>

  <description>
    <p>
      Boo is a local speech-to-text overlay that captures audio from your
      microphone and transcribes it on-device using whisper.cpp. Press
      Ctrl+Shift+Space (after approving the shortcut on first launch) or
      click the Record button, speak, and the transcript is copied to the
      clipboard and pasted into the focused app.
    </p>
    <p>
      Everything runs locally, no audio leaves your machine.
    </p>
    <p>
      Preview on Linux: recording, transcription and both portal permissions
      are verified, but Boo has not yet been run on a real GNOME or KDE
      desktop. Bug reports are welcome.
    </p>
  </description>

  <launchable type="desktop-id">com.boo.app.desktop</launchable>

  <categories>
    <category>Office</category>
    <category>AudioVideo</category>
    <category>Utility</category>
  </categories>

  <supports>
    <control>pointing</control>
    <control>keyboard</control>
    <control>touch</control>
  </supports>

  <requires>
    <display_length compare="ge">360</display_length>
  </requires>

  <releases>
    <release version="0.6.2" date="2026-07-18">
      <description>
        <p>A teardown fix and internal test-coverage hardening.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Closing the dictation overlay while a recording is in progress now stops it immediately, instead of leaving a background transcription worker running until the app quits.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.1" date="2026-07-18">
      <description>
        <p>Reliability fixes and shared cross-platform model handling.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Fixes crashes and use-after-free hazards when quitting or closing dialogs mid-operation: in-flight downloads and desktop-portal requests are cancelled cleanly and worker threads are joined at exit.</li>
          <li>Model download verification (SHA-256) and best-model auto-selection now share one implementation across macOS, Linux, and Windows, so the three behave identically.</li>
          <li>Corrects the release version stamping so every platform's artifacts report the same version.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.5.0" date="2026-07-17">
      <description>
        <p>In-app model management, better transcription, and local crash capture.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>First run offers a model download dialog (curated list, progress bar, checksum-verified) on every platform, no more copy-a-curl-command.</li>
          <li>Settings gains a model switcher: one dropdown of models on disk plus downloadable ones; picking a model swaps it in place and the choice persists.</li>
          <li>Sharper transcripts: beam search on the final decode and a cleanup pass that removes repetition loops.</li>
          <li>Partial model files from interrupted downloads are detected and offered for re-download instead of failing at load.</li>
          <li>Diagnostic logging plus local crash capture; a crash report is surfaced on the next launch and never uploaded.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.4.2" date="2026-07-16">
      <description>
        <p>Adds a native ARM64 Windows build.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Windows on ARM (Copilot+ PCs, Surface, and Windows VMs on Apple Silicon) now has its own zip, rather than only an Intel build that ran under emulation.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.4.1" date="2026-07-16">
      <description>
        <p>Reliability fixes from the first automated UI test pass.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Recording silence no longer produces made-up filler text; the take ends with "no speech detected", in both batch and streaming modes.</li>
          <li>Launching without a speech model now shows the install instructions instead of exiting silently.</li>
          <li>The waveform returns to its idle colour after a recording that captured nothing.</li>
          <li>The Flatpak moves from the end-of-life GNOME 47 runtime to GNOME 50.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.4.0" date="2026-07-16">
      <description>
        <p>The consistency release: Linux now looks and behaves like the macOS build, plus a broad reliability and security pass.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>The overlay adopts the macOS design language: a stack of transcript cards with per-card copy and dismiss, the round record button that becomes a square while recording, a waveform that colours itself for idle, recording and transcribing, and a status line that always shows the hotkey and counts the seconds while you talk.</li>
          <li>Whisper no longer invents text out of silence: non-speech annotations such as [BLANK_AUDIO] are dropped, and low-confidence segments are filtered.</li>
          <li>Starting a new recording while the previous one is still transcribing is now handled safely instead of racing.</li>
          <li>The optional VAD model download is verified against a pinned checksum before use, and portal tokens now come from the system random source.</li>
          <li>The waveform stops redrawing when idle, so an open window no longer costs battery.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.3.0" date="2026-07-16">
      <description>
        <p>The Windows release: Boo gains an experimental third platform. Nothing changes on Linux.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Windows 10+ (x86_64): WASAPI audio capture, a native Win32 overlay and tray icon, the Ctrl+Shift+Space hotkey, and clipboard plus paste delivery. Compile- and test-verified in CI on real Windows runners; not yet verified by a human on real hardware, hence experimental.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.2.0" date="2026-07-16">
      <description>
        <p>The speed release: transcription moved to the GPU, a faster engine, and streaming while you talk.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>whisper.cpp upgraded to v1.9.1, and inference now runs on the GPU via Metal on Apple Silicon; it had been CPU-only.</li>
          <li>NVIDIA Parakeet is now a supported engine and the preferred model: near large-v3 accuracy at many times the speed. Drop the ggml conversion in your models directory and Boo picks it up.</li>
          <li>Streaming transcription: with a Silero VAD model, phrases are transcribed at natural pauses while you are still talking, with live text in the overlay; stopping only waits for the final phrase. The VAD model (under 1 MB) downloads automatically on first run on both platforms.</li>
          <li>With several models installed, Boo now picks the most capable one it recognizes instead of always base.en.</li>
          <li>Text lands in the target app faster after you stop dictating (macOS paste path).</li>
          <li>Building from source works on macOS 15 again.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>

    <release version="0.1.4" date="2026-07-14">
      <description>
        <p>Correctness, security, and a project-wide quality pass.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Boo now finds any whisper model, not only the one it recommends. Previously, dropping a different model where the docs said to put it was reported as "no model installed".</li>
          <li>The RemoteDesktop restore token is written owner-only (0600); it was world-readable.</li>
          <li>Fewer permission prompts: macOS asks for Accessibility only when it first needs it, and Linux no longer re-runs the shortcut approval dialog on every launch.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>

    <release version="0.1.3" date="2026-07-14">
      <description>
        <p>Fixes found by running Boo on a real GNOME desktop, and by testing it the way a new user would.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Boo now tells you when your desktop has no global-shortcuts portal. GNOME only gained one in version 48, so on GNOME 46 (Ubuntu 24.04 LTS) the hotkey cannot work for any app; previously Boo failed silently. Auto-paste is unaffected, so Boo stays usable from the Record button.</li>
          <li>Non-English dictation works. The language was hardcoded to English, which silently translated other languages instead of transcribing them; set BOO_LANG (a language code, or "auto") when using a multilingual model.</li>
          <li>A single recording is now capped at 10 minutes and stops automatically, transcribing what it captured. Previously the buffer grew without limit and could freeze the app for minutes inside whisper.</li>
          <li>The menu bar now shows when Boo is transcribing, rather than snapping straight back to idle while whisper is still working.</li>
          <li>Fixed a memory leak, a data race, and a latent use-after-free in the audio backends.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>

    <release version="0.1.2" date="2026-07-14">
      <description>
        <p>First Linux preview, and the first build for Intel Macs.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Linux ships as a Flatpak. Audio capture, transcription, the global hotkey and auto-paste are all verified; Boo has not yet been run on a real GNOME or KDE desktop.</li>
          <li>macOS now builds for Intel as well as Apple Silicon.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>

    <release version="0.1.0" date="2026-07-14">
      <description>
        <p>First release. macOS (Apple Silicon) only.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>On-device speech-to-text with whisper.cpp, audio never leaves the machine.</li>
          <li>Global hotkey (Ctrl+Shift+Space) via the GlobalShortcuts portal.</li>
          <li>Transcripts are copied to the clipboard and pasted into the focused app via the RemoteDesktop portal.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
  </releases>
</component>
